Guide to the Bailey Daniel Webb papers, 1845-2003 and undated, bulk 1950s-2003 RL.01355
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bailey Daniel Webb papers
1845-2003 and undated, bulk 1950s-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Webb, Bailey Daniel
History of Medicine Collections (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
RL.01355
9.5 Linear Feet
Early female graduate of Duke University School of Medicine (M.D., 1946) and pediatrician in private practice in Durham Co., N.C., 1949-1987. The bulk of the papers of Bailey Daniel Webb consist of histories and geneaologies of the Webb and Daniel families of North Carolina, going back to the 18th century. Materials include drafts of historical research, memoirs, clippings, pamphlets, programs, 20th century photographs, and many folders of Webb family correspondence dating from the 20th century. Family history material comprises primarily incoming and outgoing family correspondence and geneaological records (1845-2001) for the Webb, Daniel, Smith, and Stinson families and others. Some of this material was gathered by Bailey Webb's father, J. W. Webb, for his book, Our Webb Kin of Dixie. Also includes Webb's 1941 doctoral thesis and other school records (1925-1933); as well as binders and scrapbooks compiled by Webb detailing her youth and schooling, private practice and hospital career, international trips, Durham history, chiefly in community medicine and governance, and various ancestors and relatives, including N.C. judge Susie Marshall Sharp, James E. Webb, and Stephen Moore. Records containing personally-identifiable medical information, chiefly pediatric case histories, have been segregated and are closed to use.
Access Restrictions
Access restricted. Collection contains potentially sensitive medical information. Contact Research Services to request permission to access boxes containing sensitive medical information. Request permission here: https://duke.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_8fblaT2NbgbQujj
Provenance
The Bailey Daniel Webb papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2004.
Biographical Note
Bailey Daniel Webb was an early female graduate of Duke University School of Medicine (M.D., 1946) and a pediatrician in private practice in Durham Co., N.C., 1949-1987.
Collection Overview
The bulk of the collection consists of histories and geneaologies of the Webb and Daniel families of North Carolina, going back to the 18th century. Materials include drafts of historical research, memoirs, clippings, pamphlets, programs, 20th century photographs, and many folders of Webb family correspondence dating from the 20th century. Family history material comprises primarily incoming and outgoing family correspondence and geneaological records (1845-2001) for the Webb, Daniel, Smith, and Stinson families and others. Some of this material was gathered by Webb's father, J. W. Webb, for his book, Our Webb Kin of Dixie. Also includes Webb's 1941 doctoral thesis and other school records (1925-1933); as well as binders and scrapbooks compiled by Webb detailing her youth and schooling, private practice and hospital career, international trips, Durham history, and various ancestors and relatives, including N.C. judge Susie Marshall Sharp, James E. Webb, and Stephen Moore.
Papers also include memoirs, largely in verse and written by Webb's grandmother, about slaves on her father's plantation; and an album of sayings related to "Poplar Forest," a home built by Thomas Jefferson, where a relative lived in 1970. The album's cover has an early photograph of the house pasted on. There is also a small amount of information on the histories of Wilson and Wright high schools in North Carolina and a few church histories as well.
Other folders making up approximately a quarter of the collection contain Bailey Webb's professional correspondence and papers relating to her career as a pediatrician and medical community leader in various towns and cities of North Carolina. Correspondents include members of the Trent and Semans families. Includes Webb's diplomas, typewritten memoirs of her career, begining with her medical school training at Duke in the 1940s. A few of these volumes contain patient information and photos - these are currently closed to use.
Related Material
Webb family papers, 1795-1960
Southern Historical Collection, Wilson Library, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill
Durham County (N.C.) -- History; North Carolina -- Social life and customs; North Carolina -- History; Pediatric practice -- History; Women physicians -- United States; Schools, medical -- North Carolina -- 20th century; Pediatricians -- North Carolina; Slavery -- North Carolina -- History; Scrapbooks; Durham County (N.C.) -- Politics and government; Photographs; Webb, Bailey Daniel; Webb family; Stinson family; Smith family; Duke University. School of Medicine -- History; Daniel family; History of Medicine Collections (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
- Webb family correspondence (Box 1)
- Related families correspondence (Adams, Gilliam, Callahan) (Box 1)
- James E. Webb and Edith Webb Williams correspondence (Box 1)
- Letter and cards (Box 1)
- Clippings about Webb family (Box 1)
- Webb family correspondence (Box 2)
- Kate and Bob Williamson correspondence (Box 2)
- Katherine Field Jensen correspondence (Box 2)
- Travel binder (Box 3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Itineraries, photographs, and notes from three trips titled "Tour of Europe with Kate Williamson (1956)," "Bob and Kate and Bailey 'go West' (1972)," "People to People Tour Oslo, Leningrad, Moscow, and Vienna (1977)."
- Letter of W.J. and Sue D. Webb (Box 3)
- Wright Refuge event binder, 2001 Nov. 1 (Box 3)
- Sawney Webb Reunion (Box 3)
- Thompson Webb, Jr. and III (Box 3)
- Ed Price family (Box 3)
- Mary Strughold correspondence (Box 3)
- Susie Marshall Sharp (Box 4)
- Family records binder (Box 4)
- Memoirs of Harriet Bailey Bullock Daniel (1849-1934) as recorded by Alice Goodridge Daniel (1877-1966) (Box 5)
- James Webb (Box 5)
- W.J. Webb, Our Web Kin of Dixie (Box 5)
- James Webb correspondence (Box 5)
- Lincoln Community Health Center binder (Box 6)
- Greensboro alumni clippings and announcements (Box 6)
- Publications featuring Bailey Daniel Webb (Box 6)
- Wes Williams family correspondence (Box 7)
- G. B. Lucas family correspondence (Box 7)
- Yearbook, 1932 (Box 7)
- Memoir notes on personal education, Bailey Daniel Webb (Box 7)
  Binder covers memoir notes from preschool to graduate work. Included is a copy of her thesis.
- North Carolina Pediatric Society: Child immunizations (Box 8)
- North Carolina Pediatric Society: Wright Refuge School (Box 8)
- North Carolina Pediatric Society: Lawsuit reform (Box 8)
- Pediatric Private Practice (Box 8)
- Trent and Semans Christmas cards, 1949-1990 (Box 8)
- Trent and Semans Christmas cards, 1991-2003 (Box 9)
- Semans correspondence (Box 9)
- Christmas photographs: Blarne and Irene Nashold's family (Box 9)
- Christmas photographs: Ed and Betty Hodges (Box 9)
- Webb genealogical information (Box 9)
- Julian S. Carr correspondence (Box 10)
- Family photographs (Box 10)
- Family legal documents, 1845-1940 (Box 10)
- Our Webb Kin, letters without family information (Box 10)
- W.J. Webb, Old Times Back Yonder, 1933 (Box 10)
- Clippings (Box 10)
- History of Geneva Presbyterian Church (Box 10)
- Correspondence by last name (Box 10)
- Webb family history (Box 11)
- Family reunion materials (Box 11)
- Baily Daniel Webb correspondence, 1990s-2000s (Box 11)
- Community projects correspondence, 1960s-2000s (Box 11)
- Arthur Field family correspondence (Box 12)
- Clippings (Box 12)
- Memoir of Harriet Bailey Bullock Daniel, master copy (Box 12)
- Family genealogy (Box 12)
- Bailey Daniel Webb thesis, 1941 (Box 13)
- Diploma (Box 13)
- Ferrell family history materials (Box 13)
- Wright School and Wilson School history, 1930-1940s (Box 13)
- University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill yearbook, 1939 (Box 13)
- Sue Bollock Daniel Webb genealogy, 1936 (Box 14)
- Real estate histories (Box 14)
- Family correspondence and cards (Box 14)
- Webb's curriculum vitae (Box 14)
- Duke University Founders Day materials, 1990 (Box 14)
- Duke Medical Center Senior-Student Partnership, 2003 (Box 14)
- Materials, chiefly memoirs, containing personally-identifiable medical information, 1940s-2003 (Box 15)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [Currently CLOSED to use. Please contact Research Services for information about access to these materials.]
- UNC Distinguished Alumni Award, 1998 (Box 16)
- Scrapbook (Box 16)
  Scrapbook includes materials regarding Webb and Daniel family histories, UNC and Duke medical centers and programs, Webb's career, and Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans and family.
- UNC Distinguised Alumni Award (Box 17)
- Diploma, Doctorate in Philosophy from UNC-CH (Box 17)
- Certificates of appreciation (Box 17)
- Various published versions of the Hippocratic Oath (Box 17)
  [Access to these materials restricted pending further processing. Please contact Research Services for information about access to these materials.]
- Notebook, 1990 (Box 18)
- Notebook, undated (Box 18)
- "The Incompleat Pediatrician: With Apologies to Dr. W. C. Davison", 1990 March (Box 18)
  Scope and Contents
  Small notebook of advice for pediatricians (arranged alphabetically by topic) written by Webb with the dedication "provided especially for Dr. Rebecca Trent Kirkland who already knows all of this anyway, but it may suffer from disuse atrophy." Topics include child rearing strategies for parents, including addressing misbehavior or phobias, as well as advice for diagnosing and treating common ailments (earaches, colds, broken arms, ringworm and other parasites).
- Notebook (untitled typescript) with pediatric treatments for common ailments, arranged alphabetically, undated (Box 18)